it turns into durga if you treat her
properly and I didn't use durga because
i wanted to show that i'm actually got
accused by someone that being a racist
because i because they said well you use
the endo goddess to indicate chaos and
like the greco-roman goddess to indicate
benevolence and that was obviously an
indication of life anyways it isn't i
just wanted to show that the idea of the
benevolent goddess isn't limited to a
single culture you know there's diana
she's got a lot of brass that's what's
that's what's down her front there so
she's like them though the nourishing
element of of being that's the best way
to think about it and the nourishing
element of being emerges in this sort of
fashion so that's the differentiation of
the archetype so way at the back there's
the predatory serpent chaos that lurks
in the background and then that
fragments out is one more
differentiating swap out in one
direction into the feminine you know in
the feminine this is a tough one because
there's this weird interaction here with
with gender and archetype you know so so
here's other thing
and I'm floundering the both on this
because I have for a long time because
it's very difficult which gender of
person are you most likely to see on the
cover of men's magazine a woman what
generally most likely see on the cover
of women's magazine okay why why is that
yes that's right I think that's why I
think that's why and that means that
they're both possessed by the same
archetype in a different way and the
archetype is the archetypal feminine
fundamentally and for women the
archetypal feminine is a judge and an
ideal the judges will how far do you
deviate from that the ideal is to what
degree can you emulate and then for men
it's the same damn thing the judge
elements exactly the same thing and the
possession element well it's slightly
different but it's not that different
you know so but it's a strange thing
because the visual image general digital
image is that of the feminine so it's a
strange because I don't think the
archetypal structures work the same and
women and so are people the way of
trying to figure this out is like the
Sun the hero is the Sun like the male
not the shiny Sun no it's also that it's
like but women obviously have an element
of them that can be heroic and
adversarial just like men but then in
women that's complicated because the
other primary element of their being is
the maternal feminine element and so but
that's complicated because women or men
can also be quite maternal like for
Mallos predatory mammals manner
unbelievably nurturing and feminine you
know risen bears we just eat our own
cows you know so mannered
they're quite feminine as well as being
masculine so I kind of think of it this
way it's like if you're thinking about
what your are
personality structure is is for men the
hero is at the forefront and the mother
the feminine mother is sort of behind
that and for women it's reversed the
feminine mother is sort of forefront and
the heroes behind them but both of the
archetypes are are are operative so so
you can think about that you can see
what you see what you make of it but you
know because you might say well why
would women is it reasonable to
presuppose but for women the feminine
represents the unknown just like he does
for men and I don't think it is just
like it is for men because I think for
women there's an element of the
patriarchal structure that's more
unknown than it is for men you know and
I think you see the reaction to that in
part you see the raptures of that in the
feminist movement because the patriarchy
is like the tyrannical father you know
and the patriarchy exists but it's not
the tyrannical father is not the entire
substrate of culture it's just
ridiculous but I think because women are
you know in some sense they're outsiders
to the male dominance hierarchy that the
male dominance art is more contaminated
by the unknown for women than it is for
men and I think it's more likely to be
interpreted as the tyrannical father
because of that so anyways I can't
exactly sort it out because you end up
with nested problems you know so insofar
as your primary mode of being as
feminine than your secondary mode of
being is masculine you're going to have
all the characteristics of something
masculine and all the characteristics of
something feminine but the manner in
which they manifest themselves is going
to be different and I just can't sort
that out to em clunky plus I think that
that is what we're sorting out right now
in our culture you know ever since women
got the ability to control the
reproductive function which was probably
at least in part a consequence of an a
priori psychological transformation
because you could say well the pill
freed women but then you could say well
what was the precondition for creating a
society in which the person who invented
the pill didn't get killed you know
because the Catholic Church for example
how people build was invented seriously
not happy and no wonder you know so
obviously there had to be some shifting
in the underlying conceptual landscape
in relationship to the relationship
between men and women for that invention
to even have come about you know and I
think you can really see that starting
know if you read the classic Russian
novels you can see that the push towards
equality that characterized women was
really alive and well in 19th century
Russian among the aristocrats Caucasus
so you know like it has a pretty lengthy
history the waning you mean that
widening widening of personality
differences so five differences they're
wider I don't know I don't know how to
answer that exactly so the point is that
if you look at personality differences
between men and women in the modern
world the most egalitarian cultures have
the biggest personality differences the
gender differences and so the technical
reason for that is all the environmental
variability has been eliminated that's
all that's left is genetic variability
and there's and that's not masks in some
sense by the environmental variability
so it's powerful and profound but it
definitely shows that there's a lot of
powerful genetic variability
it's a powerful evidence for that you
know but it also could be you know it
could easily be that in this society
what you're aiming for in an egalitarian
society is the right for everyone to be
different in their own way whatever that
happens to be you know and obviously
that's going to be a limited right to
some degree so an egalitarian society
wouldn't necessarily eradicate
personality differences that would be a
bloody totalitarian societies like get
rid of all the differences to the degree
that you're a female and whatever the
hell that means fundamentally and I'm
male if we have to be the same then
that's going to be a function of intense
control on the part of the state you
know to degree that that's intrinsic
we don't know what how much of its
intrinsic I would be very hesitant to
say not I mean but it's also a
prerequisite for long-term relationships
between men and women right if we work a
lot the same or at least capable of
being the same then we wouldn't
understand each other at all I mean I
don't know if we do what we do we do
more than other creatures of our
complexity that's for sure so yeah and
you know it's certainly the case that if
you look at a given individual and you
look at the variability of their
personnel feelings behaviors the
variability within a person is generally
greater than the average variability
within a population so you know human
beings if you're an extrovert you can be
extremely introverted like there's not
very many extroverts at a funeral know
the noisiest people at a funeral will be
the extroverts but they're going to be
hardly noisy at all you know and an
introvert can party themselves in the
situation where they can't shut up you
know so there's a lot of entry
individual variability I actually think
that one of the indexes of psychological
health is the maximization of individual
variability because you should be able
to be extremely compassionate for
example when you're dealing with a sick
baby you know and extremely
uncompassionate when
dealing with someone who's you know
using their illness as an excuse not to
pull their own weight but you need both
of those right and you know you'll end
up with an average point as a
consequence of your genetic structure
and maybe your your socialization and
it's sort of up to you that widen
yourself out across the full spectrum so
that you can call on those abilities
when it's necessary I think that's part
of what differentiation as a person
actually means you know because you you
come to be able to do more things and so
you can match yourself much more
carefully to the immediate demands of
the situation so yeah we have the
questions okay so the the symbol for for
anomaly the feminine differentiates into
the negative feminine and the positive
feminine part of the issue is how do you
get more of the positives and keep the
negative that thing and you know that's
that's a question that people have to
ask themselves at the person of
individual at the level of individual
interaction with other people and with
themselves but then it also works as a
representation of the unknown and nature
as such it's because in some ways those
are the same thing so that's you know
that's a differentiation so so this is
the relationship between the hero
archetype and the feminine so what you
have here is the chaos dragon
differentiating itself into the feminine
which is half positive and half negative
and the feminine they're being
manifested in the form of that's the
Virgin Mary with Christ on her lap it's
a using you saw the same representation
we were looking at Isis and Horus and
what's really quite cool about that is
you see she's surrounded by this this
mandala this this you know almond shaped
opening fundamentally and you see this
is something that Renaissance artists
did a lot you see along the edges of the
mat door
so these little baby heads that are
popping up with wings on them and those
are called poutine you know it's very
common that when you see representations
of married with-with-with like the
cosmos sort of billowing out behind her
because that's what you see it's like a
hole into time and space that there's
all these potential beings that are
surrounding her you know it's these
little baby heads with wings what the
hell are they well what is this thing
you know it's so straight right I went
to a museum in New York were a number of
Renaissance paintings of this type work
were arrayed in this one room that's
like a room with affiliate dollars
almost amazing room and there were
people all from all over the world and
they're looking at these damn paintings
they see you know this it's like it's
Mary and she's sitting on the moon and
there's a bunch of like winged baby
heads around her and everybody's looking
at this cap them on the shoulder and you
say why did you travel from Lane
Cincinnati to come to this museum to
look at what this woman do we don't even
believe in sitting on the crescent moon
surrounded by a baby heads I don't know
I've no idea why they're there
they're fascinated by the painting
they're gonna conjure up some reasons
with you know you don't even notice how
absurd it is till you take the picture a
part of it what the hell are these
things these poutine you know I think
what they are our potential beings
that's the representation so Mary
represents the the feminine domain from
which potential being emerges which is
perfectly reasonable way of
characterizing a feminine archetypes you
know what are the pictures I will show
you which I just love is married it's
another representation of Mary and she's
got Christ in her hands and she's
holding him up to the left and her foot
your foot is go on a snake's head which
is so cool because if you look at that
picture and you strip away the
judeo-christian presuppositions and you
just look at it like a damn biologist do
you think well of course that's what
she's doing you know it's like mama
Jim keeps the damn infant away from the
snakes and that's the archetype and of
course it's the archetype because that
is what you do
that's what you do when you're a mother
especially if you have nice edible
babies that snakes like to eat and that
isn't certainly something that
characterized us in our evolutionary
past so it's no wonder it's a divine
archetype you know of course it is how
could it not be you might say well I
don't believe in that was like hell does
that mean you don't believe in that
no I I didn't even understand what that
means
you know is that the mother of God and
what you mean you know what depends on
how much divinity is embodied in your
child and believe me once you have that
child you're gonna think hey there's a
pretty big chunk of divinity embodied in
that child no one will snakes gonna get
back I'm gonna keep it away from
predators and you know evil doers and
try to raise it into the best possible
thing it's like you may say you don't
believe that what the hell do you know
insofar as you're a good mother you'll
be acting that out like math and I'm not
gonna say that's wrong because I
actually think it's right I think the
child is a container of the divine and
that your job as a mother is to a lot of
that child to facilitate the development
of that child into the mythological hero
that's what you're up to and that's a
holy mission insofar as you could use
that word to describe anything and I
failed to see how that is not real I
think it's the most real thing so but I
also think the degree to which you're
going to be able to do that as a mother
it will be the most rewarding thing you
ever do in your life and you'll figure
that out it's a powerful thing and your
whole life can change us completely once
you have your own child it's like
they're not like other children they're
your old child it's like they're the
most important thing in the world right
then and from then on if you're healthy
it's like your priority shift it's not
you anymore and that's a sacrifice you
know it's a real sacrifice it's a
sacrifice that women are called on to
make it's a major sacrifice okay so then
you know the mother gives birth to the
hero okay that's Hercules it's not
Christ it's Hercules in this particular
representation and she's I love this
representation it's so cool
so Hercules he's out there in the
darkness on the water so it's the watery
chaos so that's where he's situated
himself voluntarily and he is in this
container now it's a good thing you can
think about that as a maternal container
or you can think about it as cultural
protection doesn't really matter and
then he's got this Club and if you look
on the club it's got these weird bombs
but if you look at the bumps what you
understand is those aren't bumps those
are eyes so he's just like murder he's
got this club then what's the club it's
like attention that's it you know what
if you're gonna club something you make
multi-speed a attention to it maybe it's
like a rampaging lion and you turn away
from it well it's gonna eat you so the
clubs useless without the attention but
you know the picture says a club which
is a weapon a weapon is a meta is a form
of meta attention story I thought every
person attention is a meta weapon it's
the ultimate weapon against unknown and
so there's Hercules he's got his eyes
wide open he's peering out into the
darkness he's got this lion head on and
that's because he killed the lion you
know men used to do that know the
neighbors Shepherds out in the desert
and in the Middle East one of the things
they
to do was kill a lion with a spear it's
like that's really worth thinking about
man that's hard to do that that would be
very hard to be very frightening to do
that and so but men used to do that so
that's really something to think about
anyway so he's got this lion suit on and
a lion is king of the beasts roughly
speaking so it represents the thing that
set the talk with the doorman in Turkey
you all know that because otherwise he
could have understood the Lion King and
the lion is a solar beast because it's
yellow but it weren't so you know it's a
daylight creature it's out there of them
felt where everything's sunny so its
associated with the Sun and illumination
and enlightenment so it's like lions sun
sun with eyes goes out to conquer the
unknown that's what the mother does if
she raises the proper Sun right now
she's also doing that for the daughter
but again that's complicated because
women are complicated and then their
role is very very complex and so to some
degree they're the hero but to some
degree they're the mother of the hero
and those are I would say I don't know
it you could say
you could say that in some sense a
conscious mother gives up her own
individual heroism as a sacrifice to the
potential heroism of her children you
know and that's worth thinking about
because my guess is that for most of you
your mother did that you know now you
want to you know we have my wife had a
dream once about putting on her
great-grandmother's shoes her
grandmother she she really liked her
grandmother a very feminine person and
only you know cookie making apple pie
baking piano playing
grandmother she had him down preparing
love people in the old folks home even
when she was 18 she was really cheerful
and tough but she is a great person I
really liked her but when my wife Jane
Diversey dreamt she was trying on her
shoes and the shoes were too small you
know and that was very interesting
because what she came he came to me was
the and she loved her grandmother them
there's no doubt that that role despite
her grandmother having fulfilled that so
well it wasn't enough and you know women
have kind of kind of decided that and
maybe that's for the best because now
there's all these smart women running
around doing useful things and you know
that's probably good but exactly how to
sort that out was not yet being figured
out so what time is it